Hello everyone and welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
My name is Katherine and today we've got a
very special lesson for you all about time.
That's right, we're
going to concentrate a
little bit on some
specific points of grammar
this time and we're
going to talk about the
morning routine, what
you do in the mornings.
Well, let's take a look
first at the word routine.
This is our vocabulary preview for today.
Very vocabulary preview.
Alright so A routine or the
morning routine, what is a routine?
A routine is basically your
habit for a certain period of time.
So for example your
routine in the morning is
what you do when you wake
up, get breakfast and go to work.
You can also have an evening routine, it's
what you always do before you go to bed.
Exactly, so everyone
has a routine, what they
do in the mornings, maybe what
you do at night before going to bed.
So that's what we're
going to talk about today.
That's right, you can also
have an exercise routine.
So basically anything with steps, 1, 2,
3, 4, 5 that you always do the same way.
That's exactly right.
So that's what we're
going to take a look at
today when we jump right into our
dialogue and listen to Stephanie's routine.
Stephanie, did you just get to school but
you were up in about when I left the dorm
this morning, that was
about an hour and a half ago.
This happens all the
time, why do you always
take so long to get
ready in the mornings?
It's a skill, what can I say?
I don't know why, I
just have a long routine.
Please explain because
it makes no sense to
me, how can a girl's
routine be so complicated?
You get up, you shower, you get dressed,
you brush your teeth, you're out the door.
For now or tops?
Jacob, you have the luxury of having
a haircut that rarely needs styling.
I don't, I have to set aside about an hour
and a half to get ready in the mornings.
Every day, I wake up and
head straight for the shower.
Every second day, I wash my hair.
If it's a hair washing
day, I frequently need
to wash my hair twice
because it gets really oily.
Then I usually put in a conditioner
and have to rinse that out too.
Once my hair is so long, I sell to manage
to take a shower in under 20 minutes.
Afterwards, I often
put on a pot of coffee
and get dressed while
I wait for it to brew.
I take a long time to get
dressed in the morning.
Every now and then I
remember to choose my
outfit the night before, but
usually I do it in the morning.
In all, getting dressed takes
about half an hour, at which time
my hair is now semi-dry so
then I can have to sound my hair.
Anytime to time, I'll put my hair up,
but oftentimes I blow dry it straight.
And then, because of
the texture of my hair,
I regularly have to flat iron
it to keep it from frizzing.
That's another 20 minutes or so.
After that, I have my daily makeup routine.
True, I hardly ever see you
without your hair done and your
makeup on, even when you
show up to class and sweatpants.
Tell me, how long does it take you
to choose that outfit in the morning?
Not funny.
Alright, we're back so obviously
she has a very complicated routine.
I don't know if all girls are like this.
I'm not like this, but I think a
lot of girls and some guys are.
Really?
I don't want to be sexist here.
I know some guys who take
their time in the morning and
are very, very particular
about the way that they look.
Wow.
Well yeah, I imagine
everyone has their morning
routine in different ways
and it was interesting
to see how she described it so why
don't we take a look at language takeaway.
So today's language
takeaway, like I said
at the beginning of the
podcast is all about time.
So we're going to look at some
of these important time adverbs.
That's right.
These are called
adverbs of frequency and
basically they are telling
us how we do things.
If we do something
all the time or if we
never do something or
everything in between.
Exactly.
So the first couple we have today
are a very, very common words.
You're going to hear these a lot.
The first one is
frequently, okay, frequently.
So if you do something
frequently, consider
it to be about 75% of the time, maybe
a little bit more almost 85% of the time.
Right.
So it's not always, but it's very often.
So for example, so I
frequently forget to
take my keys when I'm leaving the
house, which is a very big problem.
Exactly.
So considering out of seven days,
maybe you forget your keys five days.
Not so good.
All right.
So that's frequently.
Now let's move on to another
one that's actually a lot less.
We talk about seldom.
Well, Marco has told me
that he seldom forgets his keys.
That means he almost always remembers them.
Right.
So seldom is a negative adverb.
It's saying that almost never, okay.
So if I say for example, I
seldom go to the movies.
That's too bad.
I like the movies.
All right.
Well, that means that I maybe go
to the movie theater once a month.
Yeah, not very often seldom.
All right.
Now going back to a
positive adverb frequency,
we have often you described
frequently as very often.
That's right.
So I could also say I often forget my
keys or it often rains in tropical places.
This means this is a common thing.
Exactly.
So again, let's consider it to
be about 70 to 80% of the time.
Now with pronunciation, some
people like to pronounce often, right?
They kind of leave out the strong T
sound while other people say often.
Both forms are correct, right?
Yes.
They're both correct.
So you're safe using either of these.
Right.
Okay.
And our third adverb of
frequency, no, our fourth.
And our fourth adverb of frequency is
also a positive one and we say usually.
Really means this is something
that you do pretty consistently.
I usually brush my
hair before I go to sleep.
That means not always,
but almost every day.
Right.
So let's consider that of
seven days you do it six times.
Yeah.
I usually do this.
Okay.
So usually is again, very, very common.
And something in between maybe 60% of the
time, 50% of the time, we say regularly.
Well, I think of the word regularly as
being very closely related to regular.
So basically, if I have a schedule,
I do the same thing every day.
I do it regularly.
But sometimes there's a
special occasion, for example.
I regularly run five kilometers
after work when I go to the gym.
But sometimes when I want to
go out with my friends, I don't run.
Right.
So it's not always,
but it is pretty regular.
Exactly.
So regularly means you do it very
often, but there are some exceptions.
Okay.
Now, those are our
adverbs of frequency, but
we have a couple of other
phrases that are very similar.
So we want to take a look at those as well.
Let's go back to the
beginning of Stephanie's
routine when he said
that every day I wake up.
Okay.
So every day means 100% of the time every
single day, Monday to Sunday, exactly.
So obviously you wake up every day
or I brush my teeth twice every day.
So that's 100% of the time.
Now if we say every second
day, what does that mean?
That means Monday, yes, Tuesday, no,
Wednesday, yes, Thursday, no, or any day.
So basically, she says, I wash
my hair every second day.
That means one day I wash
my hair, but the next day I don't.
The day after that though, I
wash it again every second day.
Okay.
So you can say every
second day and I think
you can also say every
other day, every other day.
So every other day or every second
day, he calls his mother every other day.
Very good.
All right.
And she also said that every now and
then I remember to choose my outfit.
Okay.
Well, this one's interesting.
This is not very frequent.
And this is basically saying
sometimes, sometimes.
So now and then every now
and then means I sometimes do it.
I sometimes don't do it.
Every now and then I
really want to eat chocolate.
So I buy a candy bar.
Okay.
So maybe you want to eat
chocolate twice in a month.
Yeah, not very often.
Not very often.
Okay.
And another one that's very
similar is from time to time.
So Marco said that he doesn't
go to the movies very frequently.
So he goes from time to time, right.
So I can say I seldom
go to the movies or I
can say I like to go to the
movies from time to time.
That's right.
Or this girl is describing her appearance.
She says from time to
time, I put my hair up.
So that means most
of the time, that means
sometimes it's down,
sometimes it's up, right.
So as you can see,
there are many different
ways of describing the
frequency or how many
times you do certain
actions or your routine, right?
So you can use this with a lot
of things when you're describing.
And we encourage you
to try some of these new
ones because a lot of English learners use
the same time adverbs whenever they speak.
So try and really use some of
these and challenge yourself.
Exactly.
All right.
So that's all we have
for language takeaway.
Why don't we move on
now to fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
Okay.
So using some of these
adverbs I could say, I can
say I regularly make a pot
of coffee in the morning.
Okay.
So a pot of coffee, you
regularly make a pot
of coffee that means you
like to drink coffee every day.
That's right.
I always need my cup
of coffee in the morning.
So I'm usually make it first thing.
So a pot of coffee,
we know what a cup of
coffee is, but a pot of
coffee, what is a pot?
What is basically the container that you
use when you brew coffee when you make it.
So you put the coffee beans in
the machine and instead of having
a cup underneath, you have
a bigger container that's a pot.
You can also also have a pot of tea.
Exactly.
It's many cups.
Usually eight or 10 cups.
All right.
And remember that's verb to brew coffee.
I think it's a very nice kind of
fancy way of saying making coffee.
Screw a pot of coffee,
I'm brewing some coffee.
All right.
So apart from coffee
and all of these things,
let's take a look at
some of the specific
phrases that she used when
she was talking about her
hair because I think her
hair is very complicated.
It is very complicated.
Sometimes she washes her hair.
Sometimes she doesn't wash her hair.
Sometimes she blow dries it straight.
Okay.
So to blow dry means
that you use a blow dryer.
That's right.
The machine that uses
electricity to blow hot air
on your hair so that
your hair will dry quickly.
But you can blow dry
your hair in many ways.
Some people have curly hair and they have
special tools for making their hair curly.
But she says she blow dries it straight.
That means she makes
it straight with hot air.
Right.
So I think the way
you do this is you take
the blow dryer and a brush
and you brush while you blow dry.
Oh, it's making lines.
I don't have long enough hair for this.
Well, maybe you are secretly one of those
guys who has a routine like this woman.
I don't think I can take this much
time in the shower and brushing my hair.
But moving on, actually, I also know
this next phrase to flat iron your hair.
Okay.
So flat iron is a noun and a verb.
So I use a flat iron or I
can flat iron in my hair.
This is a tool that we
use that's very, very hot.
Think of an iron.
It's very, very hot.
And it basically presses my hair and makes
it very, very thin and flat and straight.
Right.
So I think people that have straight hair
don't need to really flat iron their hair.
But if you have very
curly hair, then you need it.
So what's the difference?
Give us the insight here, why
wouldn't you just blow dry its straight?
Why do you need to flat iron it?
Because a flat iron makes it more flat.
It makes your hair
stick together more and
it's much, much, much
hotter than a blow dryer.
Okay.
So I guess if you use
a blow dryer, then you
have puffy hair or like the next
word that she described, frizzy hair.
Okay.
So the adjective to describe
this kind of hair is frizzy.
For example, when it's
very rainy, my hair is frizzy.
That means that it sticks out.
It's very thick and not straight.
Okay.
It's not curly, but it's,
you know, it's messy.
It kind of inflates.
That's right.
It's like a little balloon.
But the verb here is to frize.
So my hair is frizzing.
Okay.
And that means that it's
getting like this, bigger or inflated.
That's right.
I also have this problem,
have it worse during
very humid or rainy days,
not so bad when it's dry.
Okay.
So I actually have a
little bit of frizzy hair.
That's why I have to use some
sort of hair gel hair gel or moose.
See, it's not because
I'm vain, it's just
because if I don't use this,
I'll come in looking like a lion.
And I don't think I might have to
insist that that happens sometimes soon.
We can take a picture and put
it on our website, Englishbod.
For sure, for sure.
All right.
So why don't we go back and
listen to the dialogue one last time.
Stephanie, did you just get to school?
But you were up and about
when I left the dorm this morning.
That was about an hour and a half ago.
This happens all the time.
Why do you always take so
long to get ready in the mornings?
It's a skill.
What can I say?
I don't know why.
I just have a long routine.
Please explain because
it makes no sense to me.
How can a girl's routine be so complicated?
You get up, you shower, you get dressed,
you brush your teeth, you're out the door.
Half an hour tops.
Jacob, you have the luxury of having
a haircut that rarely needs styling.
I don't.
I have to set aside about an hour
and a half to get ready in the mornings.
Every day, I wake up and
head straight for the shower.
Every second day, I wash my hair.
If it's a hair washing
day, I frequently need
to wash my hair twice
because it gets really oily.
Then I usually put in a conditioner
and have to rinse that out too.
Because my hair is so long, I seldom manage
to take the shower in under 20 minutes.
Afterwards, I often
put on a pot of coffee
and get dressed while
I wait for it to brew.
I take a long time to get
dressed in the morning.
Every now and then I
remember to choose my
outfit the night before, but
usually I do it in the morning.
And all getting dressed
takes about half an
hour, at which time my hair is now
semi-dry, so then I can have to saw my hair.
From time to time, I'll put my hair up.
But oftentimes I blow dry it straight.
And then because of the
texture of my hair, I regularly
have to flat iron it to
keep it from frizzing.
That's another 20 minutes or so.
After that, I have my daily makeup routine.
True, I hardly ever see you without your
hair done and your makeup on, even when you
show up to class and
sweatpants, tell me, how
long does it take you to
choose that outfit in the morning?
Not funny.
Alright, so actually talking about morning
routines and we've given you so many tools,
I think it would be a
great idea if our users
came to our site,
englishpot.com, and posted
a part of their morning
routine, trying to
use as many adverbs
of frequency as possible.
That's a great suggestion
and to get you all
started, I could give you
a little bit of my routine.
Alright, let's hear it.
Every morning when I
wake up, I turn off the
alarm, which is very
loud, and I take a shower.
I always brush my teeth and I usually brew
a pot of coffee, although sometimes I don't
have time to brew my coffee
and I wait until I arrive at my office.
I seldom choose the clothes I will wear the
night before, I almost always choose them
during the morning, and generally I
ride my bike to work, but not always.
Ok, I think in the winter you
seldom ride your bike to work.
Every once in a while, every
now and then, alright, see?
You have a perfect
example there of more or less
what we expect, but also
it would be interesting
to see if you have any
other type of routine.
I know some people
wake up in the morning
and the first thing they do, they
always walk their dog for example.
That's very nice.
Other people are very
hungry, so they almost
always eat first, right
when they wake up.
I eat before I brush
my teeth, sorry, actually,
yeah, alright, so we
want to hear from
you guys, come to englishpot.com,
we'll see everyone there, bye, bye.